I want to argue to you that in fact, politics and religion,
أريد أن أفرض لكم أن في الحقيقة ،السياسة والدين،
which are the two primary factors --
وهما العاملان الأساسيان --
not the sole, but overwhelmingly, the primary factors --
ليسا الوحيدان، لكن بأغلبية ساحقة، العوامل الأساسية--
which are driving towards a war which looks extremely likely --
التي تقود إلى حرب تبدو مرجحة للغاية --
bordering on the inevitable at this point,
التي لا مفر منها في هذه المرحلة،
whether one is in favor of that or not --
سواء أكان أحدهما يخدم الآخر أم لا--
that politics and religion are, in fact, themselves
أن السياسة والدين هما، في الحقيقة، أنفسهما
better conceptualized as kinds of technology,
يمكن تخيلهما بصورة أفضل كأنواع من التكنولوجيا
and subject to kinds of questions that we regularly consider
وتخضع لنوع من المسائل التي ننظر فيها بانتظام
in the space of conceptual design.
في مجال التصميم النظري
Here's what I mean. Politics and --
هذا ما أقصده. السياسة و--
let's focus on the political system in particular question here,
دعونا نركز على النظام السياسي والسؤال المطروح هنا على وجه الخصوص ،
which is the system of democracy.
وهو النظام الديموقراطي
Democracy, as a type of politics, is a technology
الديموقراطية، كنظام سياسي، هي تكنولوجيا
for the control and deployment of power.
لضبط و توظيف السلطة
You can deploy power in a wide range of ways.
يمكنك توزيع السلطة بطرق كثيرة.
The famous ones -- despotism is a good one;
الطرق الشهيرة ، الاستبداد هو مثال جيد.
anarchy is a way to not deploy the power in any organized way,
الفوضى ليست طريقة لتوزيع السلطة بطريقة منظمة،
to do it in a radically diffused fashion;
للقيام بذلك بصورة جذرية متوازنة.
and democracy is a set of technologies,
والديموقراطية هي مجموعة من التكنولوجيات
which have the effect of, in principle,
التي لديها تأثير على، بشكل أساسي
diffusing the power source to a large number of people
توزيع مصدر السلطة على عدد كبير من الناس
and then re-concentrating it in a smaller group of people who govern,
وإعادة تركيزها في مجموعة أصغر من الناس الذين يحكمون،
and who themselves are, in principle, authorized to govern
والذين هم، أساساً مخوّلين للحكم
by virtue of what the broader public has done.
بفضل ما قام به عدد أكبر من الناس.
Now, consider religion -- in this case Islam,
الآن، لننظر في الدين-- في هذه الحالة الإسلام،
which is the religion that, in some direct sense,
الذي هو دين، بصورة مباشرة
can be said to be precipitating what we're about to enter.
يمكن القول عنه ما نحن بصدد دخوله الآن.
Let me say parenthetically why I think that's the case,
أسمحوا لي أن أقول بين قوسين ما أعتقد أنه الإدعاء
because I think it's a potentially controversial statement.
لأنني أعتقد أنه يحتمل الجدل.
I would put it in the following equation: no 9/11, no war.
أريد وضع هذه المعادلة: لا 9/11، لا حرب.
At the beginning of the Bush administration,
في بداية عهد إدارة بوش،
when President Bush, now President Bush, was running for president,
عندما كان الرئيس بوش، الرئيس الآن بوش، كان ينافس للرئاسة،
he made it very clear that he was not interested in intervening broadly in the world.
أوضح بجلاء أنه غير راغب في التدخل على نطاق واسع في العالم.
In fact, the trend was for disengagement with the rest of the world.
في واقع الأمر، الإتجاه كان فك الإرتباط مع بقية العالم.
That's why we heard about the backing away from the Kyoto protocol, for example.
لهذا سمعنا عن التراجع عن معاهدة كيوتو، على سبيل المثال.
After 9/11, the tables were turned.
بعد 9/11، انقلبت الأمور
And the president decided, with his advisors,
وقرر الرئيس مع مستشاريه،
to undertake some kind of an active intervention in the world around us.
أن يأخذ دور فعّال بالتدخل في العالم حولنا.
That began with Afghanistan,
كانت البداية في أفغانستان،
and when Afghanistan went extremely smoothly and quickly,
وعندما كانت أفغانستان سهلة للغاية وسريعة،
a decision was made through the technology of democracy --
أُخذ قرار عبر تكنولوجيا الديموقراطية--
again, notice, not a perfect technology --
مجدداً، لاحظوا، ليست تكنولوجيا كاملة--
but through the technology of democracy
لكن عبر تكنولوجيا الديموقراطية
that this administration was going to push in the direction of another war --
بأن هذه الإدارة ستدفع بإتجاه حرب أخرى.
this time, a war in Iraq.
هذه المرة في العراق.
Now, the reason I begin by saying "no 9/11, no war"
الآن، سبب بدايتي بالقول، لا 9/11، لا حرب
is that we have to acknowledge that Islam,
أننا يجب أن نعترف بأن الإسلام،
as interpreted by a very, very small, extremely radical group of people,
وكما يفسره مجموعات متطرفة صغيرة ، صغيرة جداً من الناس،
was a precipitating cause of the 9/11 attacks --
كان السبب وراء هجمات 9/11--
the precipitating cause of the 9/11 attacks --
السبب وراء هجمات 9/11--
and as a consequence, at one degree of remove,
وكنتيجة لذلك، في نفس درجة القرابة،
the precipitating cause of the coming war that we're about to be engaged in.
سبب الحرب القادمة التي نحن على وشك المشاركة فيها.
And I would add that bin Laden and his followers
وأريد إضافة أن بن لادن وأتباعه
are consciously devoted to the goal of creating a conflict between democracy,
، مُكرسون بوعي إلى هدف خلق صراع ما بين الديموقراطية
or at least capitalist democracy, on the one hand,
أو على الأقل الديموقراطية الرأسمالية، من جانب،
and the world of Islam as they see and define it.
والعالم الإسلامي كما يرونه ويُعرفونه
Now, how is Islam a technology in this conceptual apparatus?
الآن، كيف يكون الإسلام تكنولوجيا في هذا الجهاز المفاهيمي؟
Well, it's a technology for, first, salvation in its most basic sense.
حسناً، إنه تكنولوجيا أولاً، للخلاص في أبسط معانيه.
It's meant to be a mechanism for construing the universe
من المفترض أن يكون آلية لفهم الكون
in a way that will bring about the salvation of the individual believer,
بطريقة تقدم الخلاص للفرد المؤمن،
but it's also meant by the Islamists --
لكنه يفترض أيضاً بحسب الإسلاميين--
and I use that term to mean people who believe that Islam --
وأستخدم هذا المصطلح لأعني الذين يعتقدون بأن الإسلام--
they follow the slogan, Islam is the answer to a wide range of questions,
يتبعون الشعار، أن الإسلام هو الحل لمجموعة واسعة من المسائل ،
whether they're social, or political, or personal, or spiritual.
سواء كانت اجتماعية، أو سياسية، أو شخصية، أو روحية.
Within the sphere of people who have that view,
في محيط هؤلاء الناس أصحاب هذه النظرة،
and it's a large number of people in the Muslim world
وهم عدد ضخم من الناس في العالم الإسلامي
who disagree with bin Laden in his application,
الذين يختلفون مع بن لادن وما فعله،
but agree that Islam is the answer.
لكنهم يتفقون على أن الإسلام هو الحل.
Islam represents a way of engaging the world
يمثّل الإسلام طريقة لجذب العالم
through which one can achieve certain desirable goals.
يمكن للمرء من خلالها تحقيق أهداف محددة منشودة.
And the goals from the perspective of Muslims are, in principle,
والأهداف من وجهة نظر المسلمين هي، أساساً،
peace, justice and equality,
السلام، العدالة، والمساواة،
but on terms that correspond to traditional Muslim teachings.
لكن بشروط تتوافق مع التعاليم الإسلامية .
Now, I don't want to leave a misimpression
الآن، لا اريد ترك إنطباع خاطئ
by identifying either of these propositions --
من خلال تعريف أي من هذه المقترحات--
rather, either of these phenomena, democracy or Islam -- as technologies.
بدلاً من ذلك، أي هذه الظواهر، الديموقراطية أو الإسلام، كتكنولوجيات
I don't want to suggest that they are a single thing that you can point to.
لا أريد أن أقترح أنها شيء واحد يمكنك الإشارة إليها.
And I think a good way to prove this
وأعتقد أن الطريقة الجيدة لإثبات ذلك
is simply to demonstrate to you what my thought process was
ببساطة أن أطرح عيلكم ما فكرت فيه خلال عملية الإعداد
when deciding what to put on the wall behind me when I spoke.
عند تقرير ما يجب وضعه على الشاشة خلال حديثي.
And I ran immediately into a conceptual problem:
ودخلت في الحال في مشكلة مفاهيمية--
you can't show a picture of democracy.
لا يمكن وضع صورة للديموقراطية.
You can show a slogan, or a symbol, or a sign that stands for democracy.
يمكنك وضع شعار، أو رمز، أو علامة تمثّل الديموقراطية.
You can show the Capitol --
يمكنك عرض الكونجرس--
I had the same problem when I was designing the cover
واجهتني نفس المشكلة أثناء تصميم الغلاف
of my forthcoming book, in fact --
لكتابي القادم، في الحقيقة--
what do you put on the cover to show democracy?
ماذا تضع على الغلاف لعرض الديموقراطية؟
And the same problem with respect to Islam.
ونفس المشكلة بالنسبة للإسلام.
You can show a mosque, or you can show worshippers,
يمكنك عرض مسجد، أو يمكنك عرض مصلين،
but there's not a straightforward way of depicting Islam.
لكن لا توجد طريقة مباشرة لتصوير الإسلام.
That's because these are the kinds of concepts
هذا بسبب أن هذه الأنواع من المفاهيم
that are not susceptible to easy representation.
ليست خاضعة بسهولة للتمثيل.
Now, it follows from that, that they're deeply contestable.
الآن، نستنتج من ذلك، أنها جدلية جداً.
It follows from that that all of the people in the world
نستنتج من ذلك أن الناس في كل العالم
who say that they are Muslims can, in principle,
الذين يقولون أنهم مسلمين، في الأساس،
subscribe to a wide range of different interpretations
يشتركون في مجموعة واسعة من التفسيرات المختلفة
of what Islam really is, and the same is true of democracy.
حول ما هو الإسلام حقيقة، ونفس الشيء ينطبق على الديموقراطية.
In other words, unlike the word hope,
بمعنى آخر، ليس مثل كلمة الأمل،
which one could look up in a dictionary and derive origins for,
التي يمكن البحث عنها في القاموس وتستخرج أصل لها،
and, perhaps, reach some kind of a consensual use analysis,
وربما، يمكنك الوصول الى نوع من التحليل التوافقي،
these are essentially contested concepts.
إنها في الأصل مفاهيم جدلية.
They're ideas about which people disagree in the deepest possible sense.
أنها أفكار يختلف الناس حولها في أعمق معنى ممكن لها .
And as a consequence of this disagreement,
وكنتيجة لهذا الإختلاف
it's very, very difficult for anyone to say,
من الصعب جداً جداً لأي شخص أن يقول،
"I have the right version of Islam."
"هذا هو الإسلام الصحيح "
You know, post-9/11, we were treated to the amazing phenomenon
تعرفون، عقب 9/11، تعرضنا لظاهرة مدهشة
of George W. Bush saying, "Islam means peace."
لجورج دبليو. بوش يقول، "الإسلام يعني السلام."
Well, so says George W. Bush.
حسناً، هكذا يقول جورج دبليو بوش.
Other people would say it means something else.
يقول آخرون بأنه يعني شئ آخر.
Some people would say that Islam means submission.
بعض الناس قد يقولوا أن الإسلام يعني الخضوع.
Other people would say it means an acknowledgement
آخرون قد يقولوا أنه يعني الاعتراف
or recognition of God's sovereignty.
أو الاعتراف بسيادة الله
There are a wide range of different things that Islam can mean.
هناك مجموعة كبيرة من مختلف الأشياء التي يمكن أن يعنيها الإسلام.
And ostensibly, the same is true of democracy.
وظاهرياً ينطبق الشئ نفسه على الديموقراطية.
Some people say that democracy consists basically in elections.
يقول بعض الناس أن الديموقراطية تكون أساساً في الإنتخابات.
Other people say no, that's not enough,
آخرون يقولوا لا، ذلك لا يكفي،
there have to be basic liberal rights: free speech, free press, equality of citizens.
يجب أن تكون هناك حقوق ليبرالية أساسية: حرية التعبير، حرية الصحافة، المساواة بين المواطنين.
These are contested points, and it's impossible to answer them by saying,
هذه نقاط إختلاف، ومستحيل أن تجيب عليها بالقول،
"Ah ha, I looked in the right place, and I found out what these concepts mean."
"أه ها، أنا نظرت في المكان الصحيح، ووجدت معاني هذه المفاهيم."
Now, if Islam and democracy are at present
الآن، إذا كان الإسلام والديموقراطية في الوقت الحاضر
in a moment of great confrontation,
في لحظة مواجهة عظيمة،
what does that mean?
ماذا يعني ذلك؟
Well, you could fit it into a range of different interpretative frameworks.
حسناً، يمكنك وضع ذلك في مجموعة من الأُطر التفسيرية المختلفة.
You could begin with the one that we began with a couple of days ago,
يمكنك أن تبدأ بتلك التي بدأناها قبل عدة أيام،
which was fear.
التي كانت الخوف.
Fear is not an implausible reaction with a war just around the corner
الخوف ليس رد فعل غير محتمل مع حرب قد تبدأ في الجوار
and with a very, very high likelihood that many, many people are going to die
ومع ترجيح عال جداً جداً بأن الكثير، الكثير من الناس سيموتون
as a consequence of this confrontation --
كنتيجة لهذه المواجهة--
a confrontation which many, many people
المواجهة التي الكثير، الكثير جداً من الناس
in the Muslim world do not want,
في العالم الإسلامي لا يريدونها،
many, many people in the American democracy do not want,
الكثير، الكثير من الناس في الديموقراطية الأمريكية لا يريدونها،
many people elsewhere in the world do not want,
كثير من الناس في أماكن أخرى من العالم لا يريدونها،
but which nonetheless is favored by a large enough number of people --
لكنها مع ذلك الخيار المفضل لعدد كبير كاف من الناس --
at least in the relevant space, which is the United States --
على الأقل في المكان ذا العلاقة، الولايات المتحدة--
to actually go forward. So fear is not a crazy response at all.
للمضي قُدماً. لذا فالخوف ليس إستجابة غير طبيعية على الإطلاق
And I think that that's, in fact, probably the first appropriate response.
وأعتقد أن ذلك، في الحقيقة، ربما أول استجابة مناسبة
What I want to suggest to you, though, in the next couple of minutes
ما أريد أن أقترحه عليكم، رغماً عن ذلك، في الدقائق القادمة
is that there's also a hopeful response to this.
بأن هناك رد فعل متفائل أيضاً لهذا.
And the hopeful response derives from recognizing
والإستجابة المتفائلة تبدأ من الإعتراف
that Islam and democracy are technologies.
بأن الإسلام والديموقراطية هما تكنولوجيتان.
And by virtue of being technologies, they're manipulable.
وبطبيعة أنهما تكنولوجيات، يمكن تحويرهما.
And they're manipulable in ways
وكلاهما تقبل التحوير بطرق
that can produce some extremely positive outcomes.
يمكنها أن تقدم نتائج إيجابية للغاية.
What do I have in mind?
ماذا يدور في ذهني؟
Well, all over the Muslim world there are people
حسناً، في كل العالم الإسلامي هناك أشخاص
who take Islam deeply seriously, people who care about Islam,
يأخذون الإسلام مأخذ الجد، ناس يهتمون بالإسلام،
for whom it's a source either of faith, or of civilization, or of deep values,
بالنسبة لهم هو مصدر للإيمان،أو الحضارة، أو قيم عميقة
or just a source of powerful personal identity,
أو مجرد مصدر للعزة، والهوية الشخصية،
who think and are saying loudly that Islam and democracy
الذين يعتقدون ويقولون بصوت جهير بأن الإسلام والديموقراطية
are in fact not in conflict, but are in fact deeply compatible.
في الحقيقة ليس في مواجهة، لكنهم في الحقيقة متوافقين بعمق.
And these Muslims -- and it's the vast majority of Muslims --
وهؤلاء المسلمون-- وهم أغلبية المسلمون،
disagree profoundly with bin Laden's approach, profoundly.
يختلفون بعمق مع منهج بن لادن، بعمق.
And they furthermore think overwhelmingly --
وعلاوة على ذلك يفكرون بغالبية--
again one can't speak of every person, but overwhelmingly,
مجدداً لا يستطيع أحد التحدث باسم كل الناس، لكن الغالبية،
and one can find this by reading any of the sources
ويستطيع الشخص معرفة ذلك بقراءة أي من الكتابات
that they have produced, and they're all over the Internet
التي كتبوها، وكلها متاحة عبر الإنترنت
and in all sorts of languages -- one can see that they're saying
وبكل اللغات-- يمكن للشخص أن يرى أنهم يقولون
that their concern in their own countries is primarily to free up themselves
أن القلق الرئيسي في بلدانهم أساساً في حريتهم نفسها
to have choice in the spheres of personal life,
لحق الإختيار في محيط الحياة الشخصية،
in the sphere of economics, in the sphere of politics,
في محيط الإقتصاد، في محيط السياسة،
and, yes, in the sphere of religion,
و نعم، في محيط الدين
which is itself closely regulated in most of the Muslim world.
الذي هو نفسه مقيّد في معظم البلدان الإسلامية.
And many of these Muslims further say
ويسهب كثير من هؤلاء المسلمين أكثر بالقول
that their disagreement with the United States
بأن عدم إتفاقهم مع الولايات المتحدة
is that it, in the past and still in the present,
في أنه، في السابق وما يزال في الحاضر،
has sided with autocratic rulers in the Muslim world
ساندت الحُكّام المستبدين في العالم الإسلامي
in order to promote America's short-term interests.
من أجل تعزيز مصالح أمريكا القصيرة الأجل.
Now, during the Cold War, that may have been
الآن، خلال الحرب الباردة، ربما كان هذا
a defensible position for the United States to take.
موقف دفاعي اتخذته الولايات المتحدة.
That's an academic question.
ذلك سؤال أكاديمي.
It may be that there was a great war to be fought between West and East,
ربما ذلك بفعل الحرب الضخمة بين الغرب والشرق،
and it was necessary on the axis of democracy against communism.
وكان من الضروري في محور الديموقراطية ضد الشيوعية.
And it was necessary in some way for these to contradict each other,
وكان من الضروري بعض الأحيان أن يناقضا بعضهما البعض،
and as a consequence you have to make friends wherever you can get them.
وكنتيجة لذلك يجب أن يكون لك صداقات متى ما وجدت فرصة لذلك.
But now that the Cold War is over,
لكن الآن الحرب الباردة انتهت،
there's nearly universal consensus in the Muslim world --
هناك ما يشبه الإجماع في الآراء في العالم الإسلامي--
and pretty close to the same here in the United States,
وما يقارب ذلك هنا في الولايات المتحدة،
if you talk to people and ask them --
إذا تحدثت مع الناس وسألتهم،
that in principle, there's no reason that democracy and Islam cannot co-exist.
أنه في الأساس، لا يوجد سبب لعدم تعايش الديموقراطية والإسلام.
And we see this among activist, practical Muslims,
ونرى ذلك عبر الناشطين، المسلمين العملين
like the Muslims who are presently the elected,
مثل المسلمين الذين تم إنتخابهم الآن،
parliamentary, democratic government of Turkey,
في البرلمان، في حكومة تركيا الديموقراطية،
who are behaving pragmatically, not ideologically,
الذين يتصرفون بعملية، لا بأيديلوجيا،
who are promoting their own religious values,
الذين يروجون للقيم الدينية الإسلامية،
who are elected by their own people
الذين انتخبهم شعبهم
because they were perceived as honest and sincere
لأنهم يعتبروا أمناء وصادقين
because of their religious values,
بسبب قيمهم الدينية،
but who do not think that Islam and a democratic system of governance
لكن من لا يعتقدون أن الإسلام ونظام الحكم الديموقراطي
are fundamentally incompatible.
لا يتفقان في الأساس
Now, you may say, but surely, what we've seen on television about Saudi Islam
الآن، ربما تقول، لكن بالتأكيد، ما رأيناه في التلفزيون عن الإسلام السعودي
convinces us that it can't possibly be compatible
يقنعنا بعدم إمكانية تعايشهما
with what we consider the core of democracy --
مع ما نعتبره جوهر الديموقراطية،
namely, free political choice, basic liberty and basic equality.
وهي؛ حرية الاختيار السياسي، أسس الحرية وأسس المساواة
But I'm here to tell you that technologies
لكن أنا هنا لأخبركم بأن التكنولوجيات
are more malleable than that.
مرنة أكثر من ذلك.
I'm here to tell you that many, many Muslims believe --
أنا هنا لأخبركم، بأن الكثير من المسلمين يعتقدون--
the vast majority, in fact -- in fact I think I would go so far as to say
الأغلبية العظمى، في الحقيقة-- حقيقة أعتقد أن بوسعي القول
that many Muslims in Saudi Arabia believe that the core values of Islam,
بأن الكثير من المسلمين في السعودية يعتقدون بأن جوهر الإسلام،
namely acknowledgement of God's sovereignty
تحديدا، الإعتراف بالعبودية لله
and basic human equality before God,
ومساواة البشر أمام الله،
are themselves compatible with liberty, equality and free political choice.
نفسها تتوافق مع الحرية والمساواة وحرية الاختيار السياسي.
And there are Muslims, many Muslims out there, who are saying precisely this.
وهناك الكثير من المسلمين، الكثير منهم، يقولون هذا بالضبط.
And they're making this argument wherever they're permitted to make it.
ويقولون آرائهم متى ما استطاعوا ذلك.
But their governments, needless to say, are relatively threatened by this.
لكن حكوماتهم، غني عن القول، مهددة بذلك نسبياً .
And for the most part try to stop them from making this argument.
وفي معظم الأحيان تمنعهم من تقديم هذه الحجة.
So, for example, a group of young activists in Egypt
فعلى سبيل المثال، مجموعة من الناشطين الشباب في مصر
try to form a party known as the Center Party,
يحاولون إنشاء حزب يعُرف بحزب الوسط،
which advocated the compatibility of Islam and democracy.
وهو يدعو إلى التوافق ما بين الإسلام والديموقراطية.
They weren't even allowed to form a party.
لم يُسمح لهم حتى بإقامة الحزب.
They were actually blocked from even forming a party
تم منعهم في الواقع حتى من تشكيل حزب
under the political system there. Why?
في إطار النظام السياسي هناك. لماذا؟
Because they would have done extraordinarily well.
لأنه كان من الممكن لهم النجاح بشكل غير عادي
In the most recent elections in the Muslim world --
في معظم الإنتخابات الأخيرة في العالم الإسلامي--
which are those in Pakistan, those in Morocco
التي أقيمت في باكستان، وفي المغرب
and those in Turkey -- in each case,
والتي أقيمت في تركيا-- في كل حالة،
people who present themselves to the electorate as Islamic democrats
الأشخاص الذين قدموا أنفسهم كمسلمين ديموقراطيين
were far and away the most successful vote-getters
كانوا هم الأنجح في حصد الأصوات
every place they were allowed to run freely.
في كل مكان سُمح لهم بالتنافس بحرية.
So in Morocco, for example, they finished third in the political race
لذا في المغرب، على سبيل المثال، كانوا ثالث أعلى الأصوات في التنافس السياسي
but they were only allowed to contest half the seats.
لكن سمح لهم بالتنافس على نصف مقاعد البرلمان فقط.
So had they contested a larger number of the seats,
و لو نافسوا حول المزيد من المقاعد
they would have done even better.
لكان أداؤهم أفضل من ذلك.
Now what I want to suggest to you is that the reason for hope in this case
الآن ما أريد إقتراحه لكم هو أن سبب التفاؤل في هذه الحالة
is that we are on the edge of a real transformation in the Muslim world.
أننا على حافة التحوّل الحقيقي في العالم الإسلامي.
And that's a transformation in which many sincerely believing Muslims --
وهذا التحوّل عند الكثير من المسلمين المؤمنين بحق --
who care very, very deeply about their traditions,
الذين يهتمون بشدة لتقاليدهم ،
who do not want to compromise those values --
الذين لا يريدون تسوية تلك القيم--
believe, through the malleability of the technology of democracy
يعتقدون، عبر مرونة تكنولوجية الديموقراطية
and the malleability and synthetic capability of the technology of Islam,
ومرونة وقابلية تطويع تكنولوجيةالإسلام،
that these two ideas can work together.
بأن هذه الأفكار يمكنها أن تعمل معاً .
Now what would that look like?
الآن كيف سيكون ذلك؟
What does it mean to say that there's an Islamic democracy?
ما معنى أن نقول أن هناك ديموقراطية إسلامية؟
Well, one thing is, it's not going to look identical
حسناً، هناك شيء واحد، أنها لن تبدو متطابقة
to democracy as we know it in the United States.
مع الديموقراطية التي نعرفها في الولايات المتحدة.
That may be a good thing, in light of some of the criticisms we've heard today --
ربما يكون هذا شيئاً جيداً، على ضوء بعض الانتقادات التي سمعناها اليوم،
for example, in the regulatory context -- of what democracy produces.
على سبيل المثال، في سياق التشريعات التي تنتجها الديموقراطية.
It will also not look exactly the way either the people in this room,
لن تبدو أيضاً مماثلة للطريقة التي ينظر بها الناس في هذه القاعة،
or Muslims out in the rest of the world --
أو المسلمين في بقية أنحاء العالم--
I don't mean to imply there aren't Muslims here, there probably are --
أنا لا أعني عدم وجود مسلمين هنا، قد يكون هناك--
conceptualize Islam.
يفهمون الإسلام.
It will be transformative of Islam as well.
سيكون من تيارات الإسلام أيضاً.
And as a result of this convergence,
وكنتيجة لهذا التقارب،
this synthetic attempt to make sense of these two ideas together,
هذه المحاولة المصطنعة لفهم الفكرتين معاً،
there's a real possibility that, instead of a clash
هناك إمكانية حقيقية بأن، بدلاً من الصدام
of Islamic civilization -- if there is such a thing --
للحضارة الإسلامية-- إذا كان هناك شيء من هذا القبيل--
and democratic civilization -- if there is such a thing --
والحضارة الديموقراطية--إذا كان هناك شئ من هذا القبيل--
we'll in fact have close compatibility.
في الواقع سيكونان شديدا التوافق
Now, I began with the war because it's the elephant in the room,
الآن، أنا بدأت بالحرب لأنها الفيل في القاعة،
and you can't pretend that there isn't about to be a war
ولا يمكننا إدعاء أنه لا توجد حرب على وشك الاندلاع
if you're talking about these issues.
إذا كنت تتحدث عن هذه القضايا.
The war has tremendous risks for the model that I'm describing
مخاطر الحرب هائلة بالنسبة للنموذج الذي أشرحه
because it's very possible that as a consequence of a war,
لأنه من الممكن جداً كنتيجة للحرب،
many Muslims will conclude that the United States
أن يستنتج الكثير من المسلمين بأن الولايات المتحدة
is not the kind of place that they want to emulate
ليست من النماذج التي يريدون محاكاتها
with respect to its forms of political government.
فيما يتعلق بشكل نظام الحكم السياسي
On the other hand, there's a further possibility that many Americans,
في الجانب الآخر، هناك إمكانية أخرى بأن كثير من الأمريكيين،
swept up in the fever of a war, will say, and feel, and think
إجتحاتهم حمى الحرب، سيقولون، ويشعرون، ويفكرون
that Islam is the enemy somehow --
بأن الإسلام هو العدو بشكل ما--
that Islam ought to be construed as the enemy.
أن الإسلام يجب أن يُفسّر بأنه العدو.
And even though, for political tactical reasons,
ورغماً عن ذلك، لأسباب سياسية تكتيكية،
the president has been very, very good about saying that Islam is not the enemy,
كان الرئيس جيد ، جيد جداً عندما قال أن الإسلام ليس العدو،
nonetheless, there's a natural impulse when one enters war
ومع ذلك، من الطبيعي أن تندفع مرة واحدة عند دخول الحرب
to think of the other side as an enemy.
لتفكر في الجانب الآخر كعدو.
And one furthermore has the impulse to generalize, as much as possible,
و الشخص بالإضافة إلى ذلك لديه الدافع للتعميم، بكل ما أمكن،
in defining who that enemy is.
في تحديد من هو العدو.
So the risks are very great.
لذا فالمخاطر عظيمة جداً.
On the other hand, the capacities for positive results in the aftermath of a war
في الجانب الآخر، القدرة على تحقيق نتائج إيجابية بعد الحرب
are also not to be underestimated,
لا ينبغي التقليل من شأنها أيضاً،
even by, and I would say especially by, people
حتى، أنني أريد القول خصوصاً من قبل الناس
who are deeply skeptical about whether we should go to war in the first place.
الذين لديهم شكوك حول هل يجب أن نذهب الى الحرب أصلا
Those who oppose the war ought to realize that if a war happens,
هؤلاء الذين يعارضون الحرب، يدركون أنه في حال وقوع الحرب،
it cannot be the right strategy,
لن تكون الاستراتيجية الصحيحة،
either pragmatically, or spiritually, or morally, to say after the war,
إمّا واقعياً، أو روحياً، أو أخلاقياً، لنقول بعد الحرب،
"Well, let's let it all run itself out, and play out however it wants to play out,
"حسناً، لنتتركها تُستنفد كما تشاء
because we opposed the war in the first place."
لأننا عارضنا الحرب منذ البداية."
That's not the way human circumstances operate.
هذه ليست الطريقة التي تعمل بها الظروف الإنسانية.
You face the circumstances you have in front of you
تواجه الظروف الماثلة أمامك
and you go forward.
وتمضي قدماً.
Well, what I'm here to say then is,
حسناً، ما جئت لأخبركم به إذن هو،
for people who are skeptical about the war,
أن للناس المتشككين في الحرب،
it's especially important to recognize that in the aftermath of the war
من المهم أن نعترف بأنه عقب الحرب
there is a possibility for the government of the United States
هناك إمكانية لحكومة الولايات المتحدة
and the Muslim peoples with whom it interacts
والشعوب الإسلامية التي تتفاعل معها
to create real forms of government that are truly democratic
لصنع شكل حقيقي لحكومة ديموقراطية بحق
and also truly Islamic.
وأيضاً إسلامية بحق
And it is crucial -- it is crucial in a practical, activist way --
و من البالغ للأهمية، بطريقة عملية و ناشطة،
for people who care about these issues to make sure
بالنسبة للأشخاص المهتمين بالقضايا للتأكد
that within the technology of democracy, in this system,
أن داخل إطار تكنولوجيا الديموقراطية، في هذا النظام،
they exercise their preferences, their choices and their voices
يمارسون ما يفضلون ، خياراتهم وأصواتهم
to encourage that outcome.
لتشجيع تلك النتيجة.
That's a hopeful message,
هذه رسالة مفعمة بالأمل،
but it's a message that's hopeful only if you understand it
لكنها رسالة آملة فقط إذا فهمناها
as incurring serious obligation for all of us.
كتحملنا لمسئولية خطيرة لنا جميعاً.
And I think that we are capable of taking on that obligation,
وأعتقد بأننا قادرون على تحمّل ذلك الإلتزام،
but only if we put what we can into it.
لكن فقط إذا سخّرنا ما باستطاعتنا.
And if we do, then I don't think that the hope will be unwarranted altogether.
واذا فعلنا ذلك، لا أعتقد أن الأمل لا مبرر له تماماً.
Thanks.
شكراً.